<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Guides &amp; Resources Archives | The Open Cookbook</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/guides-resources/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>An Allergy-Friendly Kitchen</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 22:13:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/cropped-Open-Cookbook_Logo-bw-1-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Guides &amp; Resources Archives | The Open Cookbook</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Stages of the Autoimmune Journey</title>
		<link>/stages-of-the-autoimmune-journey/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=stages-of-the-autoimmune-journey</link>
					<comments>/stages-of-the-autoimmune-journey/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephanie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 22:13:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guides & Resources]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9539</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Where are you on your autoimmune journey? There are many personal stages in processing and healing with autoimmune disease. It often starts with mysterious symptoms, leading to years of searching for a diagnosis, and then the relief and grief that comes with managing an autoimmune&#8230;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/stages-of-the-autoimmune-journey/">Stages of the Autoimmune Journey</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<span id="more-9539"></span>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>Where are you on your autoimmune journey?</p>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>There are many personal stages in processing and healing with autoimmune disease. It often starts with mysterious symptoms, leading to years of searching for a diagnosis, and then the relief and grief that comes with managing an autoimmune disease.</p>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Something I hear time and time again is that one of the toughest parts of living with chronic illness is the unpredictability. One moment you feel unstoppable and the next you are beyond exhausted in bed, not sure where you went &#8220;wrong.&#8221; I know that I can get into that mindset of dissecting every little thing, but please remember that you didn&#8217;t do this to yourself.</p>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Autoimmune disease flare-ups are often out of our control (stress and life happens), but through time, the ultimate goal is to learn how to listen to your body, understanding what work for you to bring your body back into balance.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AI-Journey_IG-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-9541" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AI-Journey_IG-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AI-Journey_IG-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AI-Journey_IG-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AI-Journey_IG-768x768.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AI-Journey_IG-530x530.jpg 530w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AI-Journey_IG-750x750.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AI-Journey_IG-500x500.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AI-Journey_IG.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>What are some of the common stages of the autoimmune journey?</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Stage 1: What is wrong with me?</strong></h2>



<p>For years before being diagnosed with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/hashimotos-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20351855" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hashimoto&#8217;s</a>, <a href="https://www.hss.edu/conditions_undifferentiated-connective-tissue-disease-overview.asp" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">UCTD</a>, and <a href="/what-is-eoe/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EoE</a>, I experienced a lot of mysterious symptoms like constant lightheadedness, migraines, chronic fatigue, anxiety, new food allergies and sensitivities, without any answers. It was really tough being in my twenties, feeling like something was wrong but doctors couldn&#8217;t figure it out. I had EKGs and lots of bloodwork performed but everything came back normal. I am sure this sounds familiar to so many of us.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote is-style-default"><blockquote><p>“And so it is a truth universally acknowledged that a young woman in possession of vague symptoms like fatigue and pain will be in search of a doctor who believes she is actually sick.”</p><cite>― Meghan O&#8217;Rourke, The Invisible Kingdom: Reimagining Chronic Illness</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>The &#8220;what is wrong with me&#8221; stage is long and arduous. You might even start to question if what you are feeling is actually real but trust me—you know your own body better than anyone else. Please keep searching for answers. There are doctors out there who will listen, take you seriously, and really keep digging until they figure it out.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Stage 2: Diagnosis &#8211; Relief &amp; Grief</strong></h2>



<p>Now, you finally have a diagnosis that explains your mysterious symptoms. First, you might feel a sense of relief. You now have a name for what is going on with your body and a diagnosis is in your medical chart. Next, comes the grief of having that diagnosis. This can be a very emotional stage and that is normal and perfectly okay. Take your time to feel all of the emotions. It has been a hard journey to get to this point.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Stage 3: What do I do now?</strong></h2>



<p>With more answers and a diagnosis, you feel ready to figure out next steps. I know for me this meant lots of time on Google, learning all I could about my autoimmune conditions. This step can feel overwhelming—trying to become an expert on your new diagnosis, learning the treatment options, and determining if making changes to your diet and lifestyle will work for you. Plus, there can be so much conflicting information out there you have no idea where to even start You might even join a Facebook support group or turn to other social media to connect with others who can relate to what you are going through.</p>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>It is okay to feel overwhelmed. This is an emotional time. If possible, try to take a step away from all of the research once in awhile and do the things that bring you the most joy—taking a walk in the park, drinking a cup of your favorite tea, playing with your dog, or spending time with friends. Finding support during this time can be really helpful.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Stage 4: The Ups and Downs of Autoimmune Disease</strong></h2>



<p>When you are ready to take charge , it can feel empowering. Whether that is through medication, diet, lifestyle, or all of the above. Learning to be your own advocate and learning to listen to your own body is one of the most important steps in managing an autoimmune disease.</p>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>The autoimmune journey isn&#8217;t linear but you are always moving forward. Flare-ups are often inevitable and it can feel frustrating when you finally feel like you are getting symptoms under control and then an unexpected stressful event happens. It is totally okay to feel frustrated—taking two steps forward and one step back is normal. But try to remember, healing is a process and there will be ups and downs but your are always learning how to best support your body.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Stage 5: <strong>Having the tools to live well</strong> with chronic illness</strong></h2>



<p>We all have our own unique needs and ways of living with autoimmune disease and chronic illness. But through time and learning to listen to your body, it gets easier. Not because there aren&#8217;t any ups and downs—the unpredictability of autoimmune disease is one of the hardest parts about living with a chronic condition. Stress happens, flare-ups happen, but being able to listen to your body is something that we can learn to do with experience.</p>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Having the tools that work for you, whether that is getting extra sleep and rest, focusing on including more nutrient-dense foods, taking some deep breaths, or even spending more time doing the things that bring you joy, are ways to help support your body back into balance.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>It&#8217;s a marathon, not a race </strong></h2>



<p>While the saying might be a bit cliché, it rings very true when living with chronic illness. As a Nutritional Therapy Practitioner (NTP) who lives with multiple chronic illnesses, I have experienced the ups and down and known the unpredictability very well. I know first hand how important it is to pace yourself even when you feel discouraged. Learning to manage autoimmune disease is a lifelong process and it takes time to feel confident and empowered. </p>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>I would love to connect with you and learn where you are on your autoimmune journey</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/stages-of-the-autoimmune-journey/">Stages of the Autoimmune Journey</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/stages-of-the-autoimmune-journey/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 Ways to be a Food Allergy Ally</title>
		<link>/5-ways-to-be-a-food-allergy-ally/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=5-ways-to-be-a-food-allergy-ally</link>
					<comments>/5-ways-to-be-a-food-allergy-ally/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephanie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 21:56:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guides & Resources]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Allergy Life]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8960</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever wondered how to provide better support to a friend or family member living with food allergies, becoming a true food allergy ally? Unfortunately when living with food allergies, it is very common to encounter people who make assumptions about what it is&#8230;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/5-ways-to-be-a-food-allergy-ally/">5 Ways to be a Food Allergy Ally</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<span id="more-8960"></span>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<p>Have you ever wondered how to provide better support to a friend or family member living with food allergies, becoming a true food allergy ally?</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Unfortunately when living with food allergies, it is very common to encounter people who make assumptions about what it is like to live with food allergies without actually understanding the complicated reality. In fact, people often forget that food allergies are a serious medical condition and something not to joke about.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>As someone who lives with <a href="/what-is-eoe/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EoE</a>, a gluten sensitivity, a shellfish allergy, and multiple autoimmune diseases, I know firsthand how frustrating it can be when people make assumptions about your dietary restrictions. </p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What is an ally?</strong></h2>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote is-style-default"><blockquote><p>&#8220;One that is associated with another as a helper&nbsp;<strong>:&nbsp;</strong>a person or group that provides assistance and support in an ongoing effort, activity, or struggle&#8221;</p><cite>&#8211; Merriam-Webster Dictionary</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>A food allergy ally is someone who takes the time to listen, learn, and advocate. While I don&#8217;t expect people who don&#8217;t have food allergies to &#8220;get it,&#8221; I do hope non-allergic people can take a step back and really listen to the range of experiences of individuals and their families who live with food allergies. There are a lot of preconceived notions that simply aren&#8217;t true and making unfounded assumptions can be not only emotionally hurtful but might even place someone in a potentially unsafe situation.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Food-Allergy-Ally_IG-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-8962" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Food-Allergy-Ally_IG-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Food-Allergy-Ally_IG-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Food-Allergy-Ally_IG-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Food-Allergy-Ally_IG-768x768.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Food-Allergy-Ally_IG-530x530.jpg 530w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Food-Allergy-Ally_IG-750x750.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Food-Allergy-Ally_IG-500x500.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Food-Allergy-Ally_IG.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>1. Food allergies aren&#8217;t a fad diet</strong></h2>



<p>This point is really important to remember. Food allergies, EoE, Celiac or other autoimmune diseases are serious medical conditions⁠—having to strictly avoid certain foods is not a choice. Avoiding specific foods is medically necessary and definitely NOT part of a &#8220;fad diet&#8221; to lose weight or &#8220;get healthy.&#8221; In reality, dietary restrictions do not equate to health. Instead, when living with food allergies, it is especially important to be mindful about eating a diverse diet to prevent potential nutrient deficiencies. </p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>I once had someone tell me, &#8220;I wish I had food allergies! That would be such a blessing so I could lose some weight.&#8221; This comment is incredibly shortsighted (I was fuming!) and really highlights how little people understand about the seriousness of food allergies.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; INSTEAD OF SAYING:</strong> &#8220;I wish I had allergies! You must be so healthy. If I had food allergies, I could lose weight.&#8221;</p>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; TRY THIS:</strong> &#8220;It must be so hard thinking about food 24/7. I can&#8217;t even imagine the amount of planning it must take.&#8221;</p>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>2. Having food allergies doesn&#8217;t mean living with deprivation</strong></h2>



<p>There is a misconception among some non-allergic people that if you have food allergies you live a very deprived life. While yes we might have to avoid specific foods and be extra cautious when dining out, that doesn&#8217;t mean we are hermits.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Hearing someone say &#8220;how do you even live without eating &#8216;fill in your allergen&#8217; &#8221; or that &#8220;they would rather die&#8221; than not be able to eat a specific food, is not only frustrating and overly dramatic, but potentially triggering for people with food allergies who might actually have life-threatening allergies to that specific food! Trust me—we much rather be alive than eat our food allergen.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; INSTEAD OF SAYING:</strong> &#8220;How do you live without eating ____________? I would rather die than not be able to eat that food.&#8221;</p>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; TRY THIS:</strong> &#8220;I can&#8217;t even imagine the daily challenges you experience. Let me know how I can best support you.&#8221;</p>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>3. Allergy-friendly food can be delicious and safe</strong></h2>



<p>There is nothing more annoying than when non-allergic people hear &#8220;gluten-free&#8221; or &#8220;vegan&#8221; and immediately say they could never eat that way and that your food must taste like &#8220;cardboard&#8221; without even trying it. These negative assumptions about allergy-friendly food can&#8217;t be farther from the truth.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>In reality, the food I eat is more interesting, diverse, and creative since my EoE diagnosis. Pre-EoE I never tried cassava or tigernut flour, delicious plantains were not on my radar, and it never occurred to me that you can make noodles out of daikon. Before making assumptions that allergy-friendly and gluten-free food is gross and tasteless, keep an open mind and give it a try.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; INSTEAD OF SAYING:</strong> &#8220;Allergen-free food tastes like cardboard. It is so gross! I would never be able to eat that.&#8221;</p>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; TRY THIS:</strong> &#8220;Wow, those ingredients sounds so interesting! I would love to learn more about your favorite safe foods and give them a try sometime.&#8221;</p>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>4. Food allergies are individual</strong></h2>



<p>Remember this very important point—just because your friend with food allergies can eat a specific food, does not mean it is safe for someone else with the same food allergy. Everyone has their own comfort level to what they feel safe eating. Please don&#8217;t push food on someone who says &#8220;no thank you.&#8221; They definitely have a very good reason for turning it down.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; INSTEAD OF SAYING:</strong> &#8220;My friend has the same food allergy as you and eats this all the time. You will be fine &#8211; don&#8217;t worry so much.&#8221;</p>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; TRY THIS:</strong> &#8220;I want to make sure you feel comfortable. Let&#8217;s find food that is safe for you.&#8221;</p>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>5. Food allergies = chronic health condition</strong></h2>



<p>After I was first diagnosed with EoE, a lot of people would tell me that &#8220;maybe I will outgrow my reactions&#8221; and that I would probably be able to eat that food again one day. While I realize this comment comes from a good place of trying to make people feel better and give some hope, it doesn&#8217;t help. In fact, these comments would make me so angry! It felt like people were dismissing my new reality of living with extensive food triggers. I wasn&#8217;t at a point of thinking about whether my EoE triggers might change one day. Instead, I was just trying to get through each day and figure out what foods were actually causing me the most pain.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Please remember that food allergies, EoE, and Celiac disease are chronic health conditions. Instead of asking if someone might outgrow their food allergies, just learn to listen to what their current challenges are so you can support them and be a better ally.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; INSTEAD OF SAYING:</strong> &#8220;Do you think you will outgrow your food allergies?&#8221;</p>



<p><strong>&gt;&gt; TRY THIS:</strong> &#8220;I&#8217;d love to learn more about your food allergies so I can better support you.&#8221;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/5-ways-to-be-a-food-allergy-ally/">5 Ways to be a Food Allergy Ally</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/5-ways-to-be-a-food-allergy-ally/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 Easy Steps to Minimize Toxins in the Kitchen</title>
		<link>/5-easy-steps-to-minimize-toxins-in-the-kitchen/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=5-easy-steps-to-minimize-toxins-in-the-kitchen</link>
					<comments>/5-easy-steps-to-minimize-toxins-in-the-kitchen/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephanie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2021 17:52:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guides & Resources]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=6855</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When starting out on any healing protocol such as the Autoimmune Protocol (AIP), we often focus on food first. For many people, lifestyle changes, including environmental toxins, typically come later. Let&#8217;s be honest—updating our lifestyles can be overwhelming. In many ways, lifestyle changes are much&#8230;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/5-easy-steps-to-minimize-toxins-in-the-kitchen/">5 Easy Steps to Minimize Toxins in the Kitchen</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<span id="more-6855"></span>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<p>When starting out on any healing protocol such as the <a href="https://autoimmunewellness.com/about-aip/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Autoimmune Protocol</a> (AIP), we often focus on food first. For many people, lifestyle changes, including environmental toxins, typically come later.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Let&#8217;s be honest—updating our lifestyles can be overwhelming. In many ways, lifestyle changes are much harder to control and implement compared to dietary changes. However, it is important to remember that food is only one piece of the healing puzzle. Updates to our lifestyle, including our personal environment, are equally important to consider to lessen the load on our bodies, also known as our &#8220;stress bucket.&#8221;</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Reducing our &#8220;stress bucket&#8221;</strong></h2>



<p>What exactly is our &#8220;<a href="https://www.thepaleomom.com/stress-undermines-health/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stress bucket</a>&#8220;? The &#8220;stress bucket&#8221; is a metaphor for describing the impact acute and chronic stress has on our wellbeing. It can include stressors such as physical and emotional stress, lack of sleep, inadequate hydration, inflammatory foods, food sensitivities, over exercising or lack of movement, and environmental toxins. When faced with chronic illness such as autoimmune disease, reducing our body&#8217;s &#8220;stress bucket&#8221; is key to lowering inflammation and supporting our immune systems.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>While it is important to focus on including therapeutic foods, we should also remember that our environment plays an important role in the long-term stress on our bodies. Try not to feel too overwhelmed (and stressed!) when investigating the range of environmental toxins that are in the modern world. Instead, focus on what you can change, start small and at a manageable scale that works for you. And remember—the body already has its own built-in detoxification system including your liver, kidneys, lungs, skin, gastrointestinal tract, and lymphatic system, that will help you navigate whatever toxins are thrown your way.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Let&#8217;s start in the kitchen</strong></h2>



<p>When addressing your personal environmental toxin load, I think one of the best places to start is the kitchen—a place where you probably have a bit more control. I suspect you are spending more time than ever in your kitchen, getting comfortable and making meals from scratch. So, how can you support your body even more, beyond the nourishing meals you are already preparing?</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Let&#8217;s take a look at five easy steps to help minimize environmental toxins in your kitchen.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>1. Use fragrance- &amp; dye-free dish and hand soap</strong></h2>



<p>One of the easiest first steps to take is to look at the ingredients in your dish and hand soap. Unfortunately, many detergent soaps contain harsh chemicals that might work well at cleaning your pots and pans but are very irritating or even toxic to the human body and can be absorbed through the skin.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Two big flags to look out for when selecting dish and/or hand soap is avoiding any product that uses &#8220;fragrance&#8221; and/or &#8220;dye&#8221;. The specific ingredients in &#8220;fragrance,&#8221; &#8220;natural fragrance,&#8221; and &#8220;organic fragrance&#8221; do not have to be disclosed by the manufacturer or supplier in the United States according to the Food &amp; Drug Administration (FDA) and therefore may contain any number of added <a href="https://www.ewg.org/news-insights/news/ask-ewg-what-fragrance" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">unknown chemicals</a>, including <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3018511/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">volatile organic compounds</a> (VOCs). In fact, &#8220;fragrance&#8221; is known to trigger asthma/allergies and migraines, may be an endocrine disruptor, and has even been linked to cancer.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Avoiding artificial &#8220;dye&#8221; is another important step to selecting a safer soap product. Three of the most commonly used artificial food coloring dyes (Red 40, Yellow 5, and Yellow 6) contain the carcinogen benzidine, and in a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/06/health/research/06hyper.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2007 study</a>, artificial food additives and coloring was linked to hyperactivity and ADHD in young children.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>&gt;&gt;</strong> <strong>Recommendations</strong>:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Check out the <a href="https://wordpress.thinkdirtyapp.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Think Dirty</strong></a> app and <a href="https://www.ewg.org/skindeep/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>EWG&#8217;s Skin Deep</strong></a> for in-depth search tools. These two resources are my go-to for researching personal care products.</li><li>My favorite fragrance-free dish and hand soaps:<ul><li><a href="https://www.spokin.com/allergy-friendly-restaurant-guides" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Seventh Generation Dish Soap &#8211; Free &amp; Clear</a></li><li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004YIXB3C/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B004YIXB3C&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=41bc402e0d6e13203b01f3b5ae409773" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ECOS Dish Soap &#8211; Free &amp; Clear</a></li><li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00JETTB0S/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B00JETTB0S&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=5b5019d9076e0ea9ea763b1adc5189e4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Seventh Generation Hand Soap &#8211; Free &amp; Clear</a></li><li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00ZP6UZ68/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B00ZP6UZ68&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=4244617d96b2625a9141f8c3d1b75f4c" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ECOS Pro Hand Soap &#8211; Free &amp; Clear</a></li><li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B07KY1JRNF/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B07KY1JRNF&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=d01e4841b6dc12eed17448e6cce9d8c4" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Method Hand Wash &#8211; Free &amp; Clear</a></li></ul></li></ul>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>2. Replace aluminum foil with parchment paper</strong></h2>



<p>While very small amounts of aluminum are naturally found in food, it is best to try to avoid consuming high-levels of aluminum since it is a <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24779346/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">neurotoxin</a>. Studies have shown that increased levels of aluminum might be linked to <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0946672X17308763" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">autism</a> and potentially <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00775-019-01710-0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Alzheimer&#8217;s disease</a> (levels of aluminum increase in the human brain as we age, though the connection to dementia is still unclear).</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>One simple way to help reduce aluminum intake is to make a simple swap of aluminum foil for <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001T6JTMY/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B001T6JTMY&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=f3011fbde0857419f38af90ec5ce3290" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">unbleached parchment paper</a>. Bonus—baking with parchment paper saves so much time, reducing clean-up, and I promise you won&#8217;t ever look back.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/PXL_20210914_203701755-1-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-6935" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/PXL_20210914_203701755-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/PXL_20210914_203701755-1-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/PXL_20210914_203701755-1-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/PXL_20210914_203701755-1-750x500.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/PXL_20210914_203701755-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Easy &amp; stackable glass food storage containers &#8211; perfect for meal prep</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>3. <strong>Swap out plastic for glass food storage containers</strong></strong></h2>



<p>When you start cooking most of your food at home, meal prep becomes a big part of your life and how you store food becomes pretty important. Plastic food storage containers are very common but unfortunately they may contain harmful chemicals that can leach into food, such as polycarbonate (plastic #7) that releases <a href="https://www.niehs.nih.gov/health/topics/agents/sya-bpa/index.cfm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bisphenol A </a>(BPA), a known endocrine/neuroendocrine disruptor that may contribute to infertility and a range of metabolic disorders such as PCOS.  </p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>If your budget allows, consider swapping plastic storage containers for <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B07RL66KCF/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B07RL66KCF&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=e2d21eeb6c05841397c144d42681fd6c" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glass food storage containers</a> with snap-on lids or mason jars. These glass containers are perfect for saving space in your fridge, can be used in the freezer, and they are BPA-free.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>If you are unable to make the swap from plastic to glass, there are some ways to minimize your risk to BPA exposure—be sure to never microwave your food in the plastic container and try gentle handwashing instead of using the dishwasher. </p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="655" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/jason-briscoe-7MAjXGUmaPw-unsplash-1024x655.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-6993" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/jason-briscoe-7MAjXGUmaPw-unsplash-1024x655.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/jason-briscoe-7MAjXGUmaPw-unsplash-300x192.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/jason-briscoe-7MAjXGUmaPw-unsplash-768x492.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/jason-briscoe-7MAjXGUmaPw-unsplash-750x480.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/jason-briscoe-7MAjXGUmaPw-unsplash.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@jsnbrsc?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Jason Briscoe</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/cooking-utensil?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>4. Rethink your cookware</strong></h2>



<p>Approved by the FDA in 1960, non-stick pots and pans have become a favorite in many households. Non-stick pots and pans (sometimes referred to as Teflon) consists of a <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/earth-and-planetary-sciences/polytetrafluoroethylene" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">polytetrafluoroethylene</a> (PTFE) coating on top of an aluminum base. When exposed to high-heat, PTFE can release toxic fumes known as <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4544973/#:~:text=Polymer%20fume%20fever%20is%20a,shivering%2C%20sore%20throat%20and%20weakness." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">‘polymer fume fever’</a> with symptoms like fever, sore throat, and coughing .</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>In addition, <a href="https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/nonstick-cookware-safety#TOC_TITLE_HDR_3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">perfluorooctanoic acid</a> (PFOAs) is often used in the manufacturing process of PTFEs and might still remain in the non-stick coating. PFOAs, also known as &#8220;forever chemicals,&#8221; have been linked to infertility, thyroid disorders, chronic kidney and liver disease, as well as some forms of cancer. </p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>As you begin to reassess your kitchen, what are some safer non-toxic cookware materials to consider instead?</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Cast iron</li><li>Stainless steel</li><li>Ceramic or ceramic-coated</li><li>Glass</li><li>Silicone</li></ul>



<p>For more information, I recommend checking out Phoebe Lapine&#8217;s  resource of her favorite <a href="https://feedmephoebe.com/best-non-toxic-nonstick-pans-use/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">non-toxic non-stick cookware</a>.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>While transitioning away from using non-stick cookware is an important step to take, it can definitely be a multi-staged process due to space constraints as well as personal budget. Pots and pans aren&#8217;t cheap so take your time in making the switch.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>In the meantime, there are some steps you can take in the meantime to reduce toxin exposure with non-stick cookware:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Avoid cooking on high-heat</li><li>Never preheat an empty pan</li><li>Use wooden or silicone cooking utensils to prevent scratching</li><li>Try to avoid stacking the pans or use paper towels or a soft fabric between each pan</li><li>Gently hand wash with a soft sponge</li><li>Replace if there are any scratches, chipping, or peeling</li></ul>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/universal-eye-frz3lprYamA-unsplash-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-6941" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/universal-eye-frz3lprYamA-unsplash-1024x576.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/universal-eye-frz3lprYamA-unsplash-300x169.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/universal-eye-frz3lprYamA-unsplash-768x432.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/universal-eye-frz3lprYamA-unsplash-750x422.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/universal-eye-frz3lprYamA-unsplash-480x270.jpg 480w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/universal-eye-frz3lprYamA-unsplash.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@universaleye?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Universal Eye</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>5. Filter your drinking water</strong></h2>



<p>Finally, water. One of the most important, if not the most important, nutrient for the human body and a top priority to research when reducing daily environmental toxins. Some of the most common toxins found in the water supply include aluminum, arsenic, chlorine, fluoride, heavy metals, PCBs, pesticides, and prescription and over-the-counter <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/pharmaceuticals-in-the-water/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">medication residue</a>.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>One of the first steps when considering your drinking water is to start with a little research about your water source. Did you know that the Environmental Working Group (EWG) has an amazing search tool called the <a href="https://www.ewg.org/tapwater/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EWG Tap Water Database</a> that you can use for free to research the details of your municipal tap water? The database collects information about what types of contaminants can be found in your zip code&#8217;s tap water and even provides suggestions for what type of filtration system to consider based on the specific contaminants.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="711" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/EWG_screenshot-1-1024x711.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-6966" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/EWG_screenshot-1-1024x711.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/EWG_screenshot-1-300x208.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/EWG_screenshot-1-768x533.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/EWG_screenshot-1-1536x1066.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/EWG_screenshot-1-750x521.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/10/EWG_screenshot-1.jpg 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Sample of EWG&#8217;s 2019 database for New York City&#8217;s tap water analysis</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>For multiple reasons, switching to filtered water turned out to be the hardest step for me to take. While I always understood the importance of drinking filtered water, I kept on reading about how great New York City&#8217;s tap water is and since I didn&#8217;t mind the taste, I just went with it. However, I finally decided to invest in a high-quality water filtration system (after much research on <a href="https://healthykitchen101.com/types-of-water-filters/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">water filtration types</a>) and it has definitely been one of the best investments I have made towards my health.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>I highly recommend the <a href="https://www.berkeyfilters.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Berkey Water Filters</a> since it is a bit more budget-friendly (I purchased the Travel Berkey &#8211; perfect for 1-2 people) compared to other high-quality options that are available. Click <a href="https://www.berkeyfilters.com/pages/filtration-specifications" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a> to review Berkey&#8217;s filter specs.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<p>I hope this list of 5 simple ways to minimize the environmental toxins in your kitchen is useful for you to consider as you take the next steps in your healing journey. It took me many years to implement these modifications due to budget and space constraints, so please don&#8217;t feel like you need to address everything all at once. Instead, prioritize what fits within your own budget and what you are most interested in tackling at this time.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>&gt;&gt;</strong> <strong>Let&#8217;s chat about toxins</strong>:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Are there any specific environmental toxins that you have encountered in your daily life that have directly impacted your health?</li><li>Are there any updates to your kitchen that have helped you move forward in your healing?</li></ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/5-easy-steps-to-minimize-toxins-in-the-kitchen/">5 Easy Steps to Minimize Toxins in the Kitchen</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/5-easy-steps-to-minimize-toxins-in-the-kitchen/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Gut-Healing: Bone Broth vs Meat Stock</title>
		<link>/gut-healing-bone-broth-vs-meat-stock/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=gut-healing-bone-broth-vs-meat-stock</link>
					<comments>/gut-healing-bone-broth-vs-meat-stock/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephanie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 21:54:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guides & Resources]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=6509</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Over the past few years, bone broth has been hailed as a key way to balance the body by reducing inflammation, fighting off colds, and healing leaky gut. Steeped in a rich history with thousands of years in culinary tradition, bone broth has been used&#8230;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/gut-healing-bone-broth-vs-meat-stock/">Gut-Healing: Bone Broth vs Meat Stock</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<span id="more-6509"></span>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<p>Over the past few years, bone broth has been hailed as a key way to balance the body by reducing inflammation, fighting off colds, and healing <a href="https://www.thepaleomom.com/what-is-leaky-gut-and-how-can-it-cause/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">leaky gut</a>. Steeped in a rich history with thousands of years in culinary tradition, bone broth has been used for supporting digestive and immune health throughout the world, including Traditional Chinese Medicine.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>While bone broth is an amazing tool to support the body through healing, it might not be the best initial step for everyone—especially when first starting out on a gut-healing protocol. Meat stock, a main staple of the <a href="https://www.gapsdiet.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GAPS Diet</a>, also has many benefits in supporting overall health, especially when faced with inflammatory digestive disorders such as Crohn&#8217;s and Ulcerative Colitis, IBS, <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/small-intestinal-bacterial-overgrowth/symptoms-causes/syc-20370168#:~:text=Small%20intestinal%20bacterial%20overgrowth%20(SIBO)%20occurs%20when%20there%20is%20an,sometimes%20called%20blind%20loop%20syndrome." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">SIBO</a>, food/chemical allergies, and <a href="https://www.entandallergy.com/blog-posts/details/your-mystery-food-sensitivity-might-actually-be-a-histamine-intolerance" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">histamine intolerance</a>.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Per the GAPS protocol developed by Dr. Natasha Campbell-McBride, meat stock can be used as a first step, sealing and healing the gut, before adding in bone broth as a final step. Let&#8217;s learn more about the differences between bone broth and meat stock, helping you decide what works best for you.</p>



<div style="height:35px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="770" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/MEAT-STOCK-vs-BONE-BROTH_WP-crop-1024x770.jpg" alt="Gut-Healing: Bone Broth vs Meat Stock" class="wp-image-6662" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/MEAT-STOCK-vs-BONE-BROTH_WP-crop-1024x770.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/MEAT-STOCK-vs-BONE-BROTH_WP-crop-300x226.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/MEAT-STOCK-vs-BONE-BROTH_WP-crop-768x578.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/MEAT-STOCK-vs-BONE-BROTH_WP-crop-1536x1156.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/MEAT-STOCK-vs-BONE-BROTH_WP-crop-2048x1541.jpg 2048w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/MEAT-STOCK-vs-BONE-BROTH_WP-crop-750x564.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/MEAT-STOCK-vs-BONE-BROTH_WP-crop-500x375.jpg 500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:35px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Bone Broth vs. <strong>Meat Stock</strong></strong></h2>



<p>Bone broth and meat stock are known for their gut-healing and soothing qualities. Bone broth primarily uses a mix of bones and joints to make the broth, while meat stock uses gelatinous meat and meaty bones. A variety of vegetables and herbs, such as celery, carrots, and parsley can be included for depth of flavor.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>One of the key differences between bone broth and meat stock is the actual cooking time. Due to the shorter cooking time of meat stock (1 to 4 hours) compared to bone broth (12 to 24 hours), meat stock in much lower in histamine and glutamine compared to traditional bone broth. Histamine and glutamine can be potential triggers for someone experiencing histamine intolerance, SIBO, MSG sensitivity, and a range of conditions associated with leaky gut.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What about the nutrients?</strong></h2>



<p>Bone broth and meat stock are both rich sources of <a href="https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/collagen#sources" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">collagen</a> and <a href="https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/gelatin-benefits#TOC_TITLE_HDR_2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gelatin</a> (a cooked form of collagen). Collagen and gelatin include the amino acids <a href="https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/glycine" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">glycine</a> and <a href="https://draxe.com/nutrition/proline/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">proline</a>. These amino acids, along with vitamin C, are necessary to support collagen formation in the body. Plus, they help strengthen and repair connective tissue, a beneficial first step when healing leaky gut.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>While meat stock is an excellent source of gelatin, bone broth has a more complete protein profile, providing higher amounts of a full range of amino acids. However, the higher levels of amino acids can make bone broth more complex to digest when first starting a gut-healing protocol. Instead, meat stock can be used which is gentler and easier on the digestive system.</p>



<div style="height:12px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Interestingly, while we often think bone broth is a rich source of minerals, <a href="https://www.alive.com/health/bone-broth-analysis-reader-research/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">studies</a> have shown that it actually isn&#8217;t a mineral-rich food source despite using bones which are inherently rich in calcium and other minerals. In fact, as Jenny McGruther, NTP of <a href="https://nourishedkitchen.com/bone-broth-minerals/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nourished Kitchen</a> points out, the low levels of minerals that are found in bone broth might actually be coming from the vegetables that are added to the broth, rather than from the bones themselves.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What if I have SIBO?</strong></h2>



<p>With SIBO, meat stock and bone broth becomes a bit more <a href="https://sibocenter.com/2016/03/bone-broth-faqs/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">complicated</a>. Since bone broth traditionally uses bones with cartilage, this can release polysaccharides (specifically glycosaminoglycans/GAGS) into the broth. <a href="https://agutsygirl.com/2013/03/01/part-v-polysaccharides/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Polysaccharides</a> may be problematic for individuals with SIBO since they can feed the bacteria in the small intestine. To reduce the amount of polysaccharides in meat stock or bone broth, try using boneless chicken/turkey breast and thighs or marrow bones, cooked for no more than a couple of hours.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Where do I begin?</strong></h2>



<p>While bone broth and meat stock are both excellent sources of gelatin and collagen, they might have their own time and place depending on where you are with healing leaky gut. According to the GAPS protocol, since bone broth is high in histamine and glutamine, it is best to start with meat stock to heal and seal the gut before moving on to bone broth. If you find that you are experiencing an increase in symptoms or reactions with bone broth, it might be worth giving meat stock a try.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Bone Broth &amp; Meat Stock Recipes</strong></h2>



<p><a href="https://bumblebeeapothecary.com/meat-stock-recipe-for-the-gaps-diet/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bumblebee Apothecary</a>, Meat Stock &#8211; Gaps Diet</p>



<p><a href="https://gapsaustralia.com.au/recipe/beef-meat-stock/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GAPS Diet Australia</a>, Beef Meat Stock</p>



<p><a href="http://www.sistersundercover.com/sibo-broth/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sisters Undercover</a>, Chicken Meat Stock for SIBO</p>



<p><a href="https://nourishedkitchen.com/bone-broth/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nourished Kitchen</a>, Bone Broth (so much fantastic info!)</p>



<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1607749319/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1607749319&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=07f784de6e2af1461b48826cb487cede" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Broth &amp; Stock</em></a> by Jenny McGruther, NTP</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/gut-healing-bone-broth-vs-meat-stock/">Gut-Healing: Bone Broth vs Meat Stock</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/gut-healing-bone-broth-vs-meat-stock/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Staying Safe: Traveling on AIP or with Food Allergies</title>
		<link>/how-to-stay-safe-traveling-on-aip-food-allergies/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=how-to-stay-safe-traveling-on-aip-food-allergies</link>
					<comments>/how-to-stay-safe-traveling-on-aip-food-allergies/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephanie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 20:00:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guides & Resources]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=6088</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you live with food allergies, celiac disease, EoE, or follow AIP (Autoimmune Protocol), you probably have experienced some level of anxiety before traveling. It can be a very stressful experience to leave the safety of your own kitchen when you have strict dietary requirements,&#8230;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/how-to-stay-safe-traveling-on-aip-food-allergies/">Staying Safe: Traveling on AIP or with Food Allergies</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<span id="more-6088"></span>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="838" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Traveling-Food-Allergies_WP-crop-1024x838.jpg" alt="food allergies travel anxiety" class="wp-image-6103" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Traveling-Food-Allergies_WP-crop-1024x838.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Traveling-Food-Allergies_WP-crop-300x246.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Traveling-Food-Allergies_WP-crop-768x629.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Traveling-Food-Allergies_WP-crop-750x614.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Traveling-Food-Allergies_WP-crop.jpg 1422w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<p>If you live with food allergies, celiac disease, <a href="/what-is-eoe/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EoE</a>, or follow AIP (<a href="https://autoimmunewellness.com/about-aip/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Autoimmune Protocol</a>), you probably have experienced some level of anxiety before traveling.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>It can be a very stressful experience to leave the safety of your own kitchen when you have strict dietary requirements, never knowing if you will have access to your safe food. To be honest, I experience some level of food-related anxiety anytime I leave my apartment, even if it is just for a few hours!</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Before being diagnosed with EoE, I never understood the numerous obstacles that go into planning vacations or even simple day-trips when living with a restricted diet. Previously, food was always a main highlight of every trip but now that I must follow a restrictive diet due to my <a href="/my-safe-foods/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EoE triggers</a>, travel looks very different and I am learning to adjust.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>I&#8217;ll never forget my first few trips traveling post-EoE diagnosis and the overwhelming fear of not bringing enough food with me. My heart would be racing for weeks, constantly brainstorming the number of meals that I would need to bring. At this point, my suitcase is mostly filled with food vs. clothing!</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>While I am still figuring out how to travel with EoE and dietary restrictions, through trial and error, I have picked up a few things that have helped me along the way. I hope these tips help you gain confidence and find joy in traveling again.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Research, Research &amp; More Research</strong></h2>



<p>Step one is to start researching everything you can about your trip destination in advance. Note: these tips are for domestic travel—I haven&#8217;t taken an international trip yet with EoE and I am sure there are a lot of other things to consider.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>First, I like to start with finding accommodations that have an in-room microwave/mini-fridge or for a longer trip, I will book an Airbnb with a kitchen. Once I narrow down some potential hotel or Airbnb options, I make sure they are located near an organic grocery store or Whole Foods, in case I need any extra safe snacks or ingredients. Finally, I love to learn more about local restaurants, searching for allergy-friendly and/or gluten-free restaurants.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>With food allergies or intolerances, researching in advance becomes even more of a priority. Luckily, we are a very resourceful crew and already have top notch planning skills!</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>&gt;&gt;</strong> <strong>Research Tips</strong>:</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Hotel with microwave/fridge or Airbnb with kitchen</li><li>Location of grocery stores (ideally close to your hotel or Airbnb)</li><li>Allergy-friendly restaurants—some great search tools:<ul><li><a href="https://www.spokin.com/allergy-friendly-restaurant-guides" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Spokin</span></a></li><li><a href="https://www.findmeglutenfree.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Find Me Gluten-Free</span></a></li><li><a href="https://www.allergyeats.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Allergy Eats</span></a></li></ul></li></ul>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Contact Restaurants In Advance</strong></h2>



<p>When I was first diagnosed with EoE, I was really nervous about reaching out directly to restaurants to find out if they could safely accommodate my food restrictions. Through time, I have discovered that reaching out via email is an amazing way to confirm if a restaurant can accommodate me. Plus, I love having it all in writing!</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>After researching allergy-friendly restaurants, I&#8217;ll create a list of top potential contenders. A couple of weeks before leaving, I will reach out to the restaurants via email and ask if they would be able to work with me to accommodate my food allergies.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>I love email because I can send them a list of my safe foods so there is nothing lost in translation. If I feel in anyway uncomfortable with the menu options that they provide me, I will be very direct and ask if they can make me something specific (such as a simple steak and steamed vegetables) and see if that is another possibility.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Typically, restaurants have been very responsive and are happy to accommodate. If a restaurant can&#8217;t accommodate my food allergies, I always appreciate their honesty. In this situation, I ask the restaurant if it is okay for me to bring my own safe meal and I have never encountered a restaurant that said no.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="700" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Restaurant-Menu_WP-crop-1024x700.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-6282" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Restaurant-Menu_WP-crop-1024x700.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Restaurant-Menu_WP-crop-300x205.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Restaurant-Menu_WP-crop-768x525.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Restaurant-Menu_WP-crop-1536x1050.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Restaurant-Menu_WP-crop-2048x1400.jpg 2048w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Restaurant-Menu_WP-crop-750x513.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption><span class="has-inline-color has-black-color">Individualized Menu at Myers+Chang in Boston, MA</span>.<span class="has-inline-color has-black-color"> What a nice touch!</span></figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Carry a food allergy chef card</strong></h2>



<p>Having a food allergy chef card on hand is an important tool to make sure there isn&#8217;t any miscommunication with the restaurant&#8217;s kitchen. I will admit, I don&#8217;t have a chef card since uncovering my EoE triggers is still a work in progress. However, I highly recommend having a chef card if this works for you.</p>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Invest in an easy to carry insulated bag</strong></h2>



<p>Investing in an insulated bag is key for traveling with food allergies. I use mine all the time, even for day trips, keeping my meals cold and safe while I am away from a fridge. I just pack up my food with some ice packs and I am ready to go!</p>



<p>My favorite <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B07KY612D4/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B07KY612D4&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=296286e8df0025fbe7202ad5674989ca" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>insulated lunch bag</strong></a> actually has two different compartments. It is perfect for storing chilled food in one compartment and snacks and a banana in another.</p>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A fridge &amp; microwave are your new best friends</strong></h2>



<p>Finding accommodations with a fridge and microwave or a full kitchen is really key to reducing stress while traveling with food allergies or on AIP.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Before booking a hotel, I always call to confirm if a mini-fridge and microwave can be provided in my room due to food allergies. Typically, most hotels can accommodate this request but sometimes they aren&#8217;t able to provide a microwave. In fact, once a hotel suggeted that I walk a few blocks away to Target and use their microwave (um, no thanks).</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Luckily, there is an amazing mini portable personal oven called <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B074TZKCCV/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B074TZKCCV&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=27be1cf088d97c1737bd15854856d1c2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>HotLogic</strong></a>. All you need is an outlet to heat up your food. This mini-oven is a definite life-saver and I highly-recommend giving it a try on your next trip if a microwave is not available.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>If I am traveling for more than a couple of nights, I make sure to book an Airbnb instead of a hotel since a kitchen will be necessary. This way, I don&#8217;t have to stress as much about bringing as many fully-prepared meals and can go grocery shopping when I arrive at my destination.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="684" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/jarek-ceborski-yw3UaP-5ybM-unsplash-1024x684.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-6433" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/jarek-ceborski-yw3UaP-5ybM-unsplash-1024x684.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/jarek-ceborski-yw3UaP-5ybM-unsplash-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/jarek-ceborski-yw3UaP-5ybM-unsplash-768x513.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/jarek-ceborski-yw3UaP-5ybM-unsplash-750x501.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/jarek-ceborski-yw3UaP-5ybM-unsplash.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Packing some kitchen basics</strong></h2>



<p>This is something that can be easily overlooked or forgotten but bringing your own kitchen basics is key, especially if you have food allergies and avoiding <a href="https://www.foodallergy.org/resources/avoiding-cross-contact" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>cross-contact</strong></a> is a priority. I always make sure to pack my own utensils, microwave-safe glass containers, a clean sponge, and dishwashing soap. </p>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Pack easy AIP / allergy-friendly snacks</strong></h2>



<p>A couple of weeks before leaving, I make sure that I have enough safe snacks for the trip. I love sourcing some easy to pack snacks that I can toss in my bag. In addition to pre-packaged snacks, I loving making a batch of AIP / Top 8 Free cookies or muffins to last a trip since they are perfect for when I am on-to-go.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong><strong>&gt;&gt;</strong> <strong>Allergy-Friendly Snack Ideas</strong>:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000FK8HJQ/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B000FK8HJQ&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=650741e65349d2afa09ce79c7e6ad84d" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Plantain Chips</span></a></li><li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B075QCXSHB/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B075QCXSHB&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=3f1d1535f7d30cda45f875265abbde13" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Pre-packaged Green Olives</span></a></li><li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B07SBKL4YQ/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B07SBKL4YQ&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=b10caf8c9ddab53ce7143ead59a2aa52" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Chomps (sea salt beef sticks)</span></a></li><li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B08BGR47CT/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B08BGR47CT&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=0f44745c02bbb234e62b500b86ee600f" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Cassava Chips</span></a></li><li><a href="https://lovebirdfoods.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Lovebird Cereal</span></a></li><li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B08LP4FYBS/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B08LP4FYBS&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=30b319cc9c0c69ed6e66a7aca2bf4763" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Freeze-dried blueberries</span></a></li><li><a href="/butternut-squash-scallion-muffins/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Butternut Squash Scallion Muffins</span></a></li><li><a href="/banana-flour-chocolate-chip-cookies/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Green Banana Flour Chocolate Chip Cookies</span></a></li><li><a href="/crispy-coconut-tigernut-cookies-aip-top-8-free/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Crispy Coconut Tigernut Cookies</span></a></li></ul>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Meal-Prep_WP-crop-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-6285" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Meal-Prep_WP-crop-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Meal-Prep_WP-crop-300x300.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Meal-Prep_WP-crop-150x150.jpg 150w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Meal-Prep_WP-crop-768x768.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Meal-Prep_WP-crop-530x530.jpg 530w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Meal-Prep_WP-crop-750x750.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Meal-Prep_WP-crop-500x500.jpg 500w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Meal-Prep_WP-crop.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption><span class="has-inline-color has-black-color">Meal Prep: <a href="/simple-roasted-carrot-fennel-soup/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Carrot Fennel Soup</span></a>, <a href="/sweet-potato-turkey-patties-aip-paleo/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Sweet Potato Turkey Patties</span></a>, Turkey/Veggies with Pesto,</span> <span class="has-inline-color has-black-color">Tigernut Cookies</span></figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Prep &amp; freeze safe meals</strong></h2>



<p>A few days before leaving for a trip, I start my meal prep and focus on meals that will be easy to transport. Soup, meat patties, and easy skillet meals are some of my go-to recipes that are filling and versatile. I also focus on meals that freeze well if I am going to be away for a couple of days or more. That way, I don&#8217;t worry about food spoiling on my journey.</p>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>It is okay to overprepare</strong> <strong>(do what is best for you)</strong></h2>



<p>Finally, it is completely normal to feel anxiety before traveling when managing food allergies or special dietary requirements. Being away from the safety of your own kitchen can be a scary experience but it definitely gets easier with time.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>We all manage anxiety in different ways. For me, I feel best when I am overprepared. While I sometimes feel ridiculous carrying a suitcase full of my safe food, this helps keep my mental health in check. Being overprepared allows for me to switch my focus to the present and enjoy all that travel has to offer.</p>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>&gt;&gt;</strong> <strong>Additional AIP &amp; Food Allergy Travel Resources</strong></h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="https://www.phoenixhelix.com/travel-series/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span class="has-inline-color has-black-color"><strong>Phoenix Helix</strong>: Paleo AIP Travel Series</span></a></li><li><a href="https://unboundwellness.com/paleo-aip-travel-food-guide-checklist/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span class="has-inline-color has-black-color"><strong>Unbound Wellness</strong>: Paleo &amp; AIP Travel Food Guide</span></a></li><li><a href="https://www.trustedtravelgirl.com/travel-articles/tips-for-traveling-with-food-allergies" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span class="has-inline-color has-black-color"><strong>Trusted Travel Girl</strong>: Tips for Traveling with Food Allergies</span></a></li><li><a href="https://thezestfull.com/how-to-cook-in-a-hotel-room/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span class="has-inline-color has-black-color"><strong>Zestfull</strong>: How to Cook in a Hotel Room</span></a></li></ul>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/how-to-stay-safe-traveling-on-aip-food-allergies/">Staying Safe: Traveling on AIP or with Food Allergies</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/how-to-stay-safe-traveling-on-aip-food-allergies/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>8 Tips For Budget-Friendly AIP Eating</title>
		<link>/8-tips-for-budget-friendly-aip-eating/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=8-tips-for-budget-friendly-aip-eating</link>
					<comments>/8-tips-for-budget-friendly-aip-eating/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephanie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 00:45:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guides & Resources]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Allergy Life]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=5230</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When I first removed gluten from my diet due to a sensitivity and Hashimoto&#8217;s thyroiditis diagnosis, I quickly realized how expensive off-the-shelf gluten-free food is priced. Gluten-free bread and crackers often cost more than double the price of standard products, so what do you do&#8230;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-tips-for-budget-friendly-aip-eating/">8 Tips For Budget-Friendly AIP Eating</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<span id="more-5230"></span>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<p>When I first removed gluten from my diet due to a sensitivity and <em><a href="https://www.thyroid.org/hashimotos-thyroiditis/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Hashimoto&#8217;s thyroiditis</a></em> diagnosis, I quickly realized how expensive off-the-shelf gluten-free food is priced. Gluten-free bread and crackers often cost more than double the price of standard products, so what do you do when your health conditions require a major shift in your food purchases?</p>



<div style="height:8px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>In 2018, I had to make even more drastic and immediate changes to my diet after being diagnosed with <a href="/what-is-eoe/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EoE</a>. Once I realized that my food sensitivities went beyond the Top 8 food-allergens, I decided to dive into the <a href="https://autoimmunewellness.com/about-aip/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Autoimmune Protocol</a> (AIP). It can be intimidating to jump into an elimination and healing diet especially when you are on a budget. Suddenly you are making major shifts in both food and lifestyle — this can feel overwhelming emotionally and financially.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>With some simple and easy tips, the AIP and other healing protocols can be an affordable and sustainable lifestyle that incorporates nutrient-dense foods into your everyday life.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/brad-stallcup-b0IELTWBvT4-unsplash_crop-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-5278" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/brad-stallcup-b0IELTWBvT4-unsplash_crop-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/brad-stallcup-b0IELTWBvT4-unsplash_crop-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/brad-stallcup-b0IELTWBvT4-unsplash_crop-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/brad-stallcup-b0IELTWBvT4-unsplash_crop-750x500.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/brad-stallcup-b0IELTWBvT4-unsplash_crop.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>1. Focus on Eating Whole Foods</strong></h1>



<p>When transitioning to AIP or any other healing protocol, you might feel like it is necessary to buy all of the amazing compliant snacks that are now readily available. I know that was my first inclination! While it is definitely important to have some convenience foods available, try to prioritize purchasing whole, unprocessed food versus specialty products. Not only will this be more cost-effective, but you will be eating a more nutrient-dense and diverse diet — a definite win-win.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>2. Eat Seasonally (or buy frozen)</strong></h1>



<p>Did you know that in-season produce is actually more nutrient-dense than out-of-season produce? Plus, in-season produce is generally more cost-effective since it doesn’t have to be shipped in from long distances. One great way to eat with the seasons is to shop at your local farmers market. A farmers market is an excellent way to support local farmers, ranchers, and vendors while having access to a fresh and diverse range of in-season organic produce.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>If a farmers market is not available to you or if your safe foods aren’t necessarily seasonal, frozen organic produce is an excellent alternative that is cost-effective. Since frozen produce is flash frozen after harvesting, fruits and vegetables typically retain similar amounts of high-quality nutrients as eating it fresh and in-season.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>3. Not Everything Has To Be Organic</strong></h1>



<p>When shopping on a tight budget, it can feel overwhelming to purchase only organic produce. If organic produce doesn’t fit within your budget, the <a href="https://www.ewg.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Environmental Working Group</a> releases a yearly guide that outlines the “Dirty Dozen” versus the “Clean Fifteen”. These two categories outline what fruits and vegetables have the most versus least amount of pesticide residue. For example, spring for organic celery, kale, and strawberries but save your money on avocado, asparagus, and kiwi.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Try your best to purchase the “Dirty Dozen” organic to keep your produce as safe and free of pesticides as possible — but don’t stress if you can’t afford or access these options. Every fruit and vegetable that is available to you helps you in your healing journey.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="719" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/tomasz-olszewski-9rt6gV_IjhA-unsplash-1-1024x719.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-5280" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/tomasz-olszewski-9rt6gV_IjhA-unsplash-1-1024x719.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/tomasz-olszewski-9rt6gV_IjhA-unsplash-1-300x211.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/tomasz-olszewski-9rt6gV_IjhA-unsplash-1-768x539.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/tomasz-olszewski-9rt6gV_IjhA-unsplash-1-750x526.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/tomasz-olszewski-9rt6gV_IjhA-unsplash-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>4. <strong>Don’t Forget To Include Herbs</strong></strong></h1>



<p>Often overlooked, herbs are key components to a nutrient-dense and flavorful diet. Not only do they provide delicious aromatics to a dish, but they are typically very cost-effective. Herbs can be purchased either fresh or dried if preferred. A fun idea to have easy access to herbs is to grow your own on a sunny windowsill or small garden (if that option is available to you). When freshly snipped and consumed right away, herbs actually contain the most micronutrients and phytonutrients available, another great incentive to try growing your own at home.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>While not an herb, I have some scallions growing in a mason jar on my kitchen windowsill that I cut from almost daily. It feels really great to connect with food in such a personal way!</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>5. Affordable Meat Options</strong></h1>



<p>It can feel intimidating when trying to source the highest-quality meat available. Luckily, there are some less-expensive options when selecting 100% grass-fed beef, bison, lamb and pasture-raised poultry.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>When purchasing high-quality meat, you don’t have to buy a fancy cut. Take a look at ground meat (my favorite budget-friendly option), stew meat, brisket, and offal — these options are much more affordable compared to other popular cuts. Also, purchasing a whole chicken is an excellent option since you will have plenty of meat to go around. Plus, you can save the bones to make a soothing bone broth (again, saving you from purchasing a specialty product).</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>While 100% grass-fed and pasture-raised is ideal due to the preferred Omega-6 to Omega-3 ratio, it isn’t always an option due to affordability and accessibility. In the article “<a href="https://www.thepaleomom.com/if-i-cant-always-afford-grass-fed-beef/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">If I Can’t Always&nbsp; Afford Grass-Fed Beef, What Should I Buy</a>?”, Dr. Sarah Ballantyne outlines some other great options to consider when purchasing meat on a budget.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/lance-grandahl-s9gqa7uTzcI-unsplash_crop-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-5271" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/lance-grandahl-s9gqa7uTzcI-unsplash_crop-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/lance-grandahl-s9gqa7uTzcI-unsplash_crop-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/lance-grandahl-s9gqa7uTzcI-unsplash_crop-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/lance-grandahl-s9gqa7uTzcI-unsplash_crop-750x500.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/lance-grandahl-s9gqa7uTzcI-unsplash_crop.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>6. Shopping Around</strong></h1>



<p>While this requires some additional planning, try taking a look at a variety of stores to find the best deals. You don’t have to shop at a health store to find great produce. Oftentimes, a standard grocery store will carry organic produce and grass-fed meat. I personally love shopping at Asian grocery stores to find a different range of vegetables, such as daikon and bok choy — remember, variety is key to nutrient-density.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>In addition, there are some fantastic resources available online. <a href="https://thrivemarket.com/myaisle/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Thrive Market</a> is my go-to online wholesale store for pantry staples such as virgin coconut oil and grain-free flours. While there is a yearly membership, I find that I save so much compared to other purchasing options. If the membership fee is out of your budget, Thrive Market accepts applications for <a href="https://thrivemarket.com/thrive-gives" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">free memberships</a> for low-income families and students in need.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>If grass-fed and pasture-raised meat is not accessible to where you live, I suggest ordering high-quality meat online. A few of my trusted sources are <a href="https://grasslandbeef.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">US Wellness Meats</a>, <a href="https://www.butcherbox.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Butcher Box</a>, and <a href="https://grassrootscoop.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Grass Roots Farmers Cooperative</a>. US Wellness Meats often has high-quality meat on sale so I always make sure to take a look for the best deals available.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>7. Keep it Simple</strong></h1>



<p>While it is tempting to want to try fancy recipes or experiment with AIP baking, these types of recipes require specialty ingredients and can be more expensive. When on a tight budget, try to keep meals simple with the highest-quality protein, fat, and carbohydrates that you can source.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>When first starting out on AIP, one of the easiest and important pantry swaps to make is to replace refined vegetable oil with high-quality fats, such as coconut oil, duck fat, tallow, and lard for higher heat cooking and to use olive oil and avocado oil for lower heat cooking or as a finishing oil. If on a tight budget, one idea is to prioritize what is most accessible to you for each category. For example, perhaps you decide to select coconut oil for high heat cooking and olive oil for low heat cooking — this is a perfect investment that covers multiple cooking methods, such as roasting, baking, stir frying, or topping a salad. This simple change will go a long way in reducing inflammation and ultimately help your cells absorb necessary vitamins and minerals, giving you long term energy.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Just remember — fancy does not mean more nutritious or flavorful. In fact, one of my favorite meals is a simple skillet meal with ground meat, a variety of different vegetables, turmeric, and coconut oil. Simple meals can be nutrient-dense and incredibly satisfying.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>8. Prioritize What Is Important To You</strong></h1>



<p>Finally, remember to prioritize what is important to you. Try to determine what you value the most and is accessible to you, while working within your budget requirements. It is easy to feel like you need to be “AIP perfect”, but try to remind yourself that you are already taking an important next step in your healing journey.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/gabriel-gurrola-fcgPRZmTM5w-unsplash-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-5268" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/gabriel-gurrola-fcgPRZmTM5w-unsplash-1024x683.jpg 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/gabriel-gurrola-fcgPRZmTM5w-unsplash-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/gabriel-gurrola-fcgPRZmTM5w-unsplash-768x512.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/gabriel-gurrola-fcgPRZmTM5w-unsplash-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/gabriel-gurrola-fcgPRZmTM5w-unsplash-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/gabriel-gurrola-fcgPRZmTM5w-unsplash-750x500.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Citations</strong></h1>



<p>Nutritional Therapy Association. (2020). <em>Basics of Nutrition </em>[PDF document].</p>



<p>Nutritional Therapy Association. (2020). <em>Culinary Wellness Part 1&nbsp; </em>[PDF document].</p>



<p>Mazzeo T, Paciulli M, Chiavaro E, Visconti A, Fogliano V, Ganino T, Pellegrini N. <em>Impact of the industrial freezing process on selected vegetables -Part II. Colour and bioactive compounds</em>. Food Res Int. 2015 Sep;75:89-97. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2015.05.036. Epub 2015 May 16. PMID: 28454976.</p>



<div style="height:65px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-tips-for-budget-friendly-aip-eating/">8 Tips For Budget-Friendly AIP Eating</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/8-tips-for-budget-friendly-aip-eating/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>8 Tips for Food Trials &#038; Reintroductions with EoE</title>
		<link>/8-tips-for-food-trials-reintroductions-with-eoe/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=8-tips-for-food-trials-reintroductions-with-eoe</link>
					<comments>/8-tips-for-food-trials-reintroductions-with-eoe/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephanie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 01:02:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guides & Resources]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=4304</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>One of the biggest challenges of living with EoE is not only facing food eliminations but the actual food reintroduction process. Since EoE is a non-IgE mediated allergic disease, it can be difficult to pinpoint what foods are causing symptoms since reactions can be delayed&#8230;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-tips-for-food-trials-reintroductions-with-eoe/">8 Tips for Food Trials &#038; Reintroductions with EoE</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<span id="more-4304"></span>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<p>One of the biggest challenges of living with <a href="/what-is-eoe/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EoE</a> is not only facing food eliminations but the actual food reintroduction process. Since EoE is a <a href="https://www.rch.org.au/uploadedFiles/Main/Content/allergy/Non%20IgE%20Food%20Allergy.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">non-IgE mediated allergic disease</a>, it can be difficult to pinpoint what foods are causing symptoms since reactions can be delayed between 24-72 hours. In addition, EoE can’t be monitored by symptoms alone and biopsies must be performed via endoscopy to confirm if a patient is reacting to a specific food.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Typically for an EoE food trial, a patient trials between one food to a small group of foods over 2-6 months before having a follow-up endoscopy. If the biopsy results come back without any eosinophils in the esophagus, the food or food group is considered safe.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Food trials can be emotionally and physically exhausting for both the patient and family. Having dedicated the past year to food reintroductions outside the Top 8 food-allergens, I wanted to share what I have learned along the way. I hope these suggestions encourage you when you might feel defeated or anxious — you aren’t alone in these feelings.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>1. Consult your medical team</strong></h1>



<p>EoE patients typically work with a gastroenterologist, allergist, and registered dietitian. Before beginning any food trial, it is important to review your food reintroduction selections and food trial process with your medical team. Since many EoE patients also have IgE-mediated food allergies, discuss with your allergist to see if you might need to undergo additional allergy testing before reintroducing a specific food.</p>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>2. Select foods for nourishment and joy</strong></h1>



<p>When I first started the food reintroduction process, I was eating roughly ten foods, all outside the Top 8 food-allergens. It was a bit overwhelming to think where do I even begin when so many foods had been eliminated.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>How do I determine what foods I want to trial?</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Select foods that will provide a more varied diet and fill-in any missing key nutrients</li><li>Try to introduce a range of food types that allow for recipe variation</li><li>Make sure to select foods that bring joy and excitement (this is also important!)</li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>For example, one of the first foods I decided to reintroduce was cassava flour since it is a calorie-rich food that is also considered to be low-allergy. In addition, it can be used in grain-free and allergy-friendly baking. Cassava flour ended up being an incredibly versatile safe food for me and I have gained a lot of nourishment and food joy from this one ingredient.</p>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>3. Face your food fear and anxiety</strong></h1>



<p>It is only natural to feel nervous and anxious about trialing a new food and you are definitely not alone. If you have experienced painful reactions to food before, it can be very triggering and scary to take that first bite.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>How do I cope with my food anxiety around reintroductions?</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Focus on positive experiences when food has been a success</li><li>Trial food in a safe environment, such as my own kitchen and home</li><li>Have a family member or friend with me, giving me support and encouragement</li><li>Take a small bite and distract myself with a movie or book — reassess how I feel in a couple of hours</li><li>Remind myself that adding a new food will lead to an expanded and more diverse diet that will help meet my nutrient requirements</li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>After finding a few foods that I was able to reintroduce with success, I started to feel more comfortable with the process. With time, I built up my confidence and feel excited to try new foods again.   </p>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>4. Don&#8217;t forget to go slow</strong></h1>



<p>Taking your time with food reintroductions is really important and something I am not always great at following. Once I feel like a food might work for me, I get really excited and I want to start adding more and more foods without taking the time to evaluate. Unfortunately, this can make it difficult to pinpoint what food is causing reactions and you might have to start over. So remember — one food reintroduction at a time.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>What process do I follow when reintroducing a food?</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Pick a day without any symptoms</li><li>Start with 1 tbsp of the new food and wait a couple of hours to evaluate</li><li>If the food seems to be okay, try again the next day. If there isn&#8217;t any reaction, wait a couple of days and try the food again, gradually building up the amount over a few days.</li><li>Don&#8217;t make any dietary changes while reintroducing the new food — keep variables as minimal as possible.</li><li>If a new food causes a reaction, stop and ask your doctor if you have any concerns. Before trialing the next food, wait for all symptoms to clear up. Sometimes, this can take up to a couple of weeks.</li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>Depending on the food, the process of reintroduction for one food can take me between 2-4 weeks. Since the reactions with EoE are delayed, I like to make sure I give enough time after eating a new food before trying anything new again. It is common for EoE patients to start feeling symptoms up to two weeks after introducing a food. </p>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>5. Time to become a detective</strong></h1>



<p>When dealing with food allergies and intolerances, it is important to become your own detective. Since the beginning of my EoE diagnosis, I have kept a highly-detailed spreadsheet that documents my food elimination and trialing progress. It is a helpful tool that I use to document both my safe foods, failed foods, and the foods that I am currently trialing.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>How do I organize the food trial spreadsheet?</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Outline each food by category, such as vegetables, fruit, herbs, meat, etc.</li><li>Create sub-categories — for example, the vegetable category is organized into roots/tubers vs. leafy greens. This organization allows for me to evaluate if there are any trends of what types of food might be safe for me.</li><li>Make sure to keep a detailed list of reactions to foods — this is really important information that can also help your medical team assess your progress and treatment.</li></ul>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>6. Listen to your body even when it is difficult</strong></h1>



<p>While I have always been hyper-aware of my body and any symptoms that I might be experiencing, finding acceptance that a food might not be working for me can still be a challenge.</p>



<p>During one of my recent food trials, I failed to be honest with myself. I was trialing pears and really wanted it to work for me since it has always been one of my favorite fruits. I made sure to eat it well-cooked, but I still reacted. I tried removing the peel before cooking, but sure enough my symptoms came back. I was so desperate to add some fruit back into my diet that I was in denial.</p>



<p>In retrospect, I knew this food wasn’t safe for me based on the symptoms I was experiencing. It can be hard to accept when a food doesn’t work for you, especially if it is something you miss.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>How do I cope with disappointment and finding acceptance when a new food is not safe?</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Focus on other things that are not food-oriented that bring me happiness — go for a walk, watch a movie, play with my cat</li><li>Remind myself of the foods that I can eat and the progress that I have made</li><li>Make myself a safe meal that is fun and enjoyable</li></ul>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>7. Discover your creativity</strong></h1>



<p>If a food reintroduction seems to be going well, now comes the fun part! As anyone with food allergies or intolerances knows, you have to become really creative with cooking since you can&#8217;t rely on standard recipes and ingredients.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>What are some ways to get creative and have fun when trialing a new food?</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li>Try different combinations of your safe foods with the reintroduced food — any new interesting flavor or textural combinations?</li><li>Experiment with a variety of cooking methods such as roasting, steaming, stir fry, etc.</li></ul>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>8. Patience</strong></h1>



<p>As cliché as this sounds, it is important to remember that living with EoE is a marathon and not a sprint.</p>



<p>EoE and other EGIDs are life-altering and can greatly impact your quality of life. It is okay to feel frustration, exhaustion, and grief. You will have good days and bad days. Foods will be safe one day and mysteriously not safe the next.</p>



<p>Just remember that the healing process is not always linear and it is perfectly okay to move at your own pace.</p>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Resources</strong></h1>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="https://www.choc.org/programs-services/eosinophilic-esophagitis/food-reintroduction/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CHOC Eosinophilic Esophagitis Clinic</a></li><li><a href="https://www.cincinnatichildrens.org/health/e/eosinophilic-esophagitis" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cincinnati Center for Eosinophilic Disorders</a></li></ul>



<p><em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/092352164X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=092352164X&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=opencookbook-20&amp;linkId=beb26b4582663c07455a43e6a8e08e9d" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dealing with Food Allergies (A Practical Guide to Detecting Culprit Foods and Eating a Healthy, Enjoyable Diet)</a></em> by Janice Vickerstaff Joneja, Ph.D., R.D.N.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-tips-for-food-trials-reintroductions-with-eoe/">8 Tips for Food Trials &#038; Reintroductions with EoE</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/8-tips-for-food-trials-reintroductions-with-eoe/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Grain-Free &#038; Nut-Free Flour Guide</title>
		<link>/grain-free-nut-free-flours/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=grain-free-nut-free-flours</link>
					<comments>/grain-free-nut-free-flours/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephanie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 11:22:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guides & Resources]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=3849</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you are new to gluten-free, grain-free, and nut-free baking, you have probably encountered a lot of alternative flour types and are feeling uncertain about where to even begin. When I first eliminated gluten, almond flour was my go-to for baking. However, after having to&#8230;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/grain-free-nut-free-flours/">The Grain-Free &#038; Nut-Free Flour Guide</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<span id="more-3849"></span>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<p>If you are new to gluten-free, grain-free, and nut-free baking, you have probably encountered a lot of alternative flour types and are feeling uncertain about where to even begin.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>When I first eliminated gluten, almond flour was my go-to for baking. However, after having to eliminate nuts, I had to turn to other flour alternatives, such as cassava flour and arrowroot powder. After making the switch, I can honestly say that I am really enjoying the variety of options available and having fun experimenting.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>It is important to note that with alternative flours, replacements are not 1:1 with original wheat flour recipes. In my experience, it definitely takes some trial and error to learn the properties of the various flours but I have discovered that mixing the flours yields the best results. It can feel intimidating trying to bake with new types of flour, but it is definitely possible to create similar textures with the right flour combinations.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="790" height="1024" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/Grain-Free_Nut-Free-Flours-labels-790x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-3858" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/Grain-Free_Nut-Free-Flours-labels-790x1024.jpg 790w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/11/Grain-Free_Nut-Free-Flours-labels-231x300.jpg 231w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/11/Grain-Free_Nut-Free-Flours-labels-768x996.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/11/Grain-Free_Nut-Free-Flours-labels-1185x1536.jpg 1185w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/11/Grain-Free_Nut-Free-Flours-labels-1580x2048.jpg 1580w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/11/Grain-Free_Nut-Free-Flours-labels-750x972.jpg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/11/Grain-Free_Nut-Free-Flours-labels-scaled.jpg 1975w" sizes="(max-width: 790px) 100vw, 790px" /></figure>



<hr class="wp-block-separator is-style-default"/>



<p>To help familiarize you with grain-free and nut-free flours, I wanted to share with you an alternative flour guide. I hope the guide gives you the confidence to try your own versions of your favorite recipes.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Arrowroot Powder</strong></h1>



<p>Light, powdery, and fluffy, arrowroot powder is extracted from the rhizomes of the tropical herb <em>Maranta arundinacea</em>. It is an easily-digestible starch that is native to South America, Mexico, and the Caribbean.</p>



<p>Arrowroot powder has a neutral flavor that can help bind together baked goods while providing some elasticity and lightness. Not only can arrowroot powder be used in baking, but it can be used as a thickening agent, acting as a perfect swap for cornstarch.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Recipes to check out:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="/rosemary-flatbread-aip/" target="_blank">AIP Rosemary Flatbread</a></li><li><a href="/easy-aip-scallion-pancakes/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Easy AIP Scallion Pancakes</a></li><li><a href="/butternut-squash-scallion-muffins/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Butternut Squash Scallion Muffins</a></li></ul>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Cassava Flour</strong></h1>



<p>One of the main staples of grain-free baking, cassava flour has a starchy texture that provides a nice chew in baked goods. It is made by drying and grinding the white flesh of the yuca root, a root vegetable native to South America.</p>



<p>Cassava flour has a texture that is similar to wheat flour, however when baked, it is pretty dense since it absorbs more liquid. I find that it works best when mixed with other alternative flours to help soften and lighten it up.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Recipes to check out:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="/pesto-pizza-with-fennel-zucchini-squash/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pesto Pizza with Fennel, Zucchini &amp; Squash</a></li><li><a href="/sweet-plantain-mini-cakes/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sweet Plantain Mini Cakes</a></li><li><a href="/top-eight-free-chocolate-chip-cookies/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Top 8 Free Chocolate Chip Cookies</a></li></ul>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Coconut Flour</strong></h1>



<p>This grain-free flour alternative is produced from drying and grinding coconut meat. When I first started baking with coconut flour, I was very surprised at how small of an amount a recipe requires. A general rule of thumb is 1/4 to 1/3 cup of coconut flour to wheat flour.</p>



<p>However, similar to other alternative flours, I find coconut flour works best if it is mixed with other flours, especially since it is so porous. It is very absorbent and high in fiber, making it great for soaking up excess liquid, such as in baked goods that call for pureed/shredded fruit or vegetables.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Recipes to check out:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="/golden-turmeric-coconut-cookies-aip-top-8-free/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Golden Turmeric Coconut Cookies</a></li><li><a href="/sweet-potato-chocolate-chip-blondies/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sweet Potato &amp; Chocolate Chip Blondies</a></li><li><a href="/sweet-plantain-mini-cakes/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sweet Plantain Mini Cakes</a></li></ul>



<div style="height:40px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Tigernut Flour</strong></h1>



<p id="block-11762e33-fcf8-41d5-8723-08ef275729e1">Despite the name, tigernut is&nbsp;<em>not</em>&nbsp;a nut. It is actually a tuber that grows on one of the only edible sedges,&nbsp;<em>Cyperus esculentus</em>&nbsp;(Yellow Nut Grass).</p>



<p id="block-fcb44078-f85d-493c-a6dd-f87701608295">Tigernut flour is very rich in prebiotic fiber, a resistant starch, making it great for gut health. It is probably my favorite alternative flour to bake with due to its naturally sweet and &#8220;nutty&#8221; flavor. Tigernut flour has a similar texture to almond flour but is nut-free. Again, I find it works best when mixed with arrowroot powder or cassava flour to help bind ingredients together.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Recipes to check out:</strong></h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="/blueberry-tigernut-muffins-aip-low-fodmap/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Blueberry Tigernut Muffins</a></li><li><a href="/banana-maple-tiger-nut-muffins/">B</a><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="/banana-maple-tiger-nut-muffins/" target="_blank">anana Maple Tigernut Muffins</a></li><li><a href="/crispy-coconut-tigernut-cookies-aip-top-8-free/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Crispy Coconut Tigernut Cookies</a></li><li><a href="/paleo-double-chocolate-banana-muffins-top-8-free/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Paleo Double Chocolate Chip Muffins</a></li><li><a href="/chocolate-coconut-cream-pie/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Chocolate Coconut Cream Pie</a></li></ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/grain-free-nut-free-flours/">The Grain-Free &#038; Nut-Free Flour Guide</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">The Open Cookbook</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/grain-free-nut-free-flours/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
